Derek Mahon papers, circa 1948-2008
Emory University
Derek Mahon papers, 1948-2008
Mahon, Derek, 1941-
Manuscript Collection No. 689
34.75 linear ft. (67 boxes) and 16 oversized papers (OP)
Papers of poet Derek Mahon, including correspondence, literary manuscripts, collected printed material, photographs, audiovisual material, legal and financial papers, subject files, and ephemera.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 1991 with subsequent additions.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: Series 1, Correspondence, selected correspondence is closed except with the permission of the letter writer. Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers. Series 10, Unprocessed additions, is closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
Derek Mahon was born in Belfast, Northern Ireland, on November 23, 1941. He was educated at the Belfast Royal Academical Institution and at Trinity College, Dublin, where he majored in French (1960-1965). In 1960 he began publishing poems in Icarus, a student literary magazine, and in 1965 he received the Eric Gregory Award for poetry. For the next few years, Mahon held a variety of teaching jobs in Ireland, England, France, Canada, and the United States. His first collection of poems, the chapbook Twelve Poems, was published by Queens University in 1965. His first major collection, Night Crossing, was published by Oxford University Press in 1968.
In 1970 Mahon moved to London where he worked as a free-lance journalist, while also serving as drama critic for the Listener (1971-1972) and features editor for Vogue (1974-1975). During the early seventies he contributed frequent reviews to the Observer, the Listener, New Statesman, and the Times Literary Supplement. Also during these years he published two more full-length collections of poems, Lives (1972) and The Snow Party (1975). In 1977 he returned to Northern Ireland as writer in residence at the New University of Ulster, Coleraine.
In 1979 a selection of Mahon's early poetry was published by Oxford University Press, Poems, 1962-1978; that same year he took a position with the BBC writing adaptations for television. Among his many television adaptations are Jennifer Johnston's Shadows on Our Skin and How Many Miles to Babylon?, and Elizabeth Bowen's The Demon Lover and The Death of the Heart.
In 1982 Mahon published The Hunt by Night, and in 1985 the chapbook Antarctica. In 1990 Derek Mahon and Peter Fallon co-edited The Penguin Book of Contemporary Irish Poetry. In 1991 he received the Lannan Foundation Prize and the following year The Irish Times-Aer Lingus Poetry Prize. After a lengthy silence, Mahon published a chapbook The Yaddo Letter in 1992, followed by the long verse sequence The Hudson Letter in 1995. A collection of his prose work was published in 1996 under the title Journalism.
In 1995 Mahon moved from New York to Dublin, where he still lives, and in the fall of 1997 Gallery Press published The Yellow Book. In 1998, he published his translations of Philippe Jacottet's poetry as Words In the Air. His Collected Poems, also published by Gallery, was released in November 1999; this collection represents, according to the publisher, "the poems the author 'wishes to preserve' from the work of forty years." Some months later, Penguin issued a shorter collection of his poems in the U.K., entitled Selected Poems (2000).
Scope and Content Note
The Derek Mahon papers are composed of correspondence, literary manuscripts, collected printed material, photographs, audiovisual material, legal and financial papers, subject files, and ephemera from 1948-2008. The papers document Derek Mahon's creative work during the last thirty years. In addition, his writing for television and the stage, as well as his journalistic writing during this period (including his regular "Letter from New York" which he contributed to The Irish Times), are well documented. The papers also include correspondence with other literary figures, including: Samuel Beckett, Sara Berkeley, Douglas Dunn, Peter Fallon, Brian Friel, Eamon Grennan, Seamus Heaney (letters by Seamus Heaney are closed without the written permission of Seamus Heaney), Anthony Hecht, Aidan Higgins, Michael Longley, W.S. Merwin, John Montague, Brian Moore, Harold Pinter, and James Simmons. Printed material, either by or about Derek Mahon or collected by him, is also present, as are photographs and financial papers from this same period.
Arrangement Note
Organized into nine series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Writings by Derek Mahon, (3) Writings by others, (4) Printed material, (5) Photographs/Audio-visual material, (6) Legal and financial papers, (7) Subject files, (8) Ephemera, (9) Collected material, and (10) Unprocessed additions.
Related Materials in This Repository
Derek Mahon collection, Michael Longley papers, Peter Fallon/Gallery Press collection;, and Medbh McGuckian papers.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Beckett, Samuel;, 1906-1989 Berkeley, Sara;, 1967- Friel, Brian;, 1948- Heaney, Seamus;, 1939- Hecht, Anthony;, 1923-2004 Longley, Michael;, 1939- Merwin, W. S. (William Stanley);, 1927- Montague, John;. Simmons, James;, 1933-
Topical Terms
English poetry-Irish authors.; French literature-Translations into English; Irish poetry-20th century.; Poets, Irish-20th century.; Stage adaptations.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Poems.; Sreenplays.
Occupation
Poet.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1972-2007, Series 1; Box 1 - Box 16a
  Scope and Content Note
  The correspondence in the Derek Mahon papers dates from 1979 to 2007 (with a two year gap of 1985-1986) and is composed largely of incoming letters from friends, editors, publishers, and other literary associates. Also present are a small number of drafts of letters by Mahon himself. Most of this correspondence relates to the various literary projects that he was engaged in during these years. Prominent correspondents include Samuel Beckett, Sara Berkeley, Douglas Dunn, Peter Fallon, Brian Friel, Eamon Grennan, Seamus Heaney (letters by Seamus Heaney are closed without the written permission of Seamus Heaney), Anthony Hecht, Aidan Higgins, Michael Longley, W.S. Merwin, John Montague, Brian Moore, Harold Pinter, and James Simmons. The collection also includes a number of letters written by Mahon to Dillon Johnstone at the Wake Forest University Press, Mahon's publisher in the United States.
  Arrangement Note
  Arranged chronologically when a date is known (in the absence of a date, postmarks have been used to file these letters). Undated letters are filed at the end of the series.
  Restrictions on Access
  Special restrictions apply: selected correspondence is closed except with the permission of the letter writer. Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
  - 1972, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1982 January-May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1982 June-August (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1982 September-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1983 January-May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1983 June-December (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1984 January-February (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1984 March-April (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1984 May-June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1984 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Undated letters (1979-1984) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Enclosures (1979-1984) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1990 January-May (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1990 June-October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1990 November-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1991 January (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1991 February (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1991 March (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1991 April (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1991 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1991 June-July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1991 August (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1991 September-October (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1991 November-December (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1992 January-February (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1992 March-April (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1992 May-August (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1992 September-October (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1992 November (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1992 December (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1993 January (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1993 February (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1993 March (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1993 April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1993 May (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1993 June (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1993 July (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1993 August (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1993 September (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1993 October 1-20 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1993 October 21-31 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1993 November (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1993 December 1-20 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1993 December 20-31 and circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1994 January (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1994 February (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1994 March (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1994 April (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1994 May (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1994 June 1-7 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1994 June 8-30 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1994 July (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1994 August (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1994 September (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1994 October (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1994 November (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1994 December (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1994 December and circa 1994 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1995 January-March (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1995 April-May (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1995 June-August (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1995 September-October (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1995 November-December (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Circa 1995 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1996 January-February (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1996 March-April (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1996 May-June (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1996 July-October (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1996 November-December and circa 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1997 January-March (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1997 April-June (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1997 July-September (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1997 October-November (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1997 December (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Circa 1997 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1998 January-February (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1998 March-May (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1998 June-August (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1998 September-November (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1998 December and circa 1998 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1999 January (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1999 February-April (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1999 May-June (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1999 July-September (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 1999 October-December and circa 1999 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 2000 January-April (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 2000 May-June (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 2000 July-August (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 2000 September-December and circa 2000 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 2001 January-April (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 2001 May-August (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 2001 September-December and circa 2001 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 2002 January-May (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 2002 June-December (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 2003 January-August (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 2003 September-December (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 2004 January-March (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 2004 April-August (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 2004 September-December and circa 2004 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 2005 January-April (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 2005 May-October (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 2005 November-December and circa 2005 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 2006 January-March (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 2006 April-July (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 2006 August-December and circa 2006 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 2007 January-March (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 2007 April-July (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 2007 August-December and circa 2007 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 14a, Folder 1)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 14a, Folder 2)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 14a, Folder 3)
  - Undated correspondence, circa 2000-2006 (Box 14a, Folder 4)
  - Undated correspondence, circa 2000-2002 (Box 14a, Folder 5)
  - Undated correspondence, circa 2002-2007 (Box 14a, Folder 6)
  - Fragment of letter from DM to unknown correspondent (Box 14a, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Christmas and birthday cards (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Christmas and birthday cards, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Christmas and birthday cards, 2000-2006 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from DM's children (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Invitations 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Invitations 1996-1997 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Invitations 1998 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Invitations 1999 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Invitations 2000-2001 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Invitations 2002-2003 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Invitations 2004-2006 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Invitations, 2007 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Invitations, circa 2000-2006 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence between Wake Forest University Press and Derek Mahon, 1976-1990 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between Wake Forest University Press and Derek Mahon, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Restricted Correspondence
  - Cahill, Christopher, Mahon to (Box 16a, Folder 1)
  - Heaney, Seamus (Box 16a, Folder 2)
  - Heaney, Seamus (Box 16a, Folder 3)
  - Heaney, Seamus (Box 16a, Folder 4)
  - McGuckian, Medbh (Box 16a, Folder 5)
  - Montague, John (Box 16a, Folder 6)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 16a, Folder 7)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 16a, Folder 8)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 16a, Folder 9)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 16a, Folder 10)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 16a, Folder 11)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 16a, Folder 12)
  - Restricted correspondence (Box 16a, Folder 13)
- Writings by Derek Mahon, 1976-2007, Series 2; Box 17 - Box 35 (folder 6); OP1-3
  The manuscripts in this series date from approximately the same time period as the above correspondence and include drafts of poems, critical writings, radio scripts, and screenplays. Derek Mahon's literary manuscripts include book-length collections and individual poems by Mahon, prose by Mahon, scripts and screenplays, works that were edited by Mahon, interviews with Mahon, translations of Mahon's work, and some of Derek Mahon's desk diaries. The poems are listed under the titles of the major trade volumes in which they first appeared. The information that Mahon recorded in his desk diaries is completely marked out and therefore indecipherable. In addition, cataloged separately and held in MARBL's book collection are Derek Mahon's working copies of The Hunt by Night (with extensive revisions), Mary Stuart, and She Came of Decent People.
  Organized into seven subseries: (2.1) Poems, (2.2) Prose, (2.3) Scripts and screenplays, (2.4) Works edited by Derek Mahon, (2.5) Interviews with Derek Mahon, (2.6) Translations of Derek Mahon's writings, and (2.7) Desk diaries.
  - Poems, Subseries 2.1; Box 17 - Box 23 (folder 6); OP1-2
    - Collected poems, Subseries 2.1a; Box 17 - Box 22 (folder 33); OP1-2
      - Lives (1972)
      - "Beyond Howth Head," TS (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Poems 1962-1978 (1979)
      - "Open Your Books and Start Reading" [variant title: title of Teaching in Belfast], TS (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - The Hunt by Night (1982)
      - "After Pasternak," TS (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - The Hunt by Night, proofs with holograph corrections (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Antarctica (1985)
      - "Antarctica," TS (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - "Craigvara House," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - "Death and the Sun," TS (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - "A Kensington Notebook," TS (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - "A Kensington Notebook," proof (Box OP1)
      - "Night Drive," TS (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - "October," TS (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - "St. Eustace," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Selected Poems (UK 1991)
      - Selected Poems, typescript with corrections (1 of 2) (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Selected Poems, typescript with corrections (2 of 2) (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Selected Poems, photocopy of proofs with holograph corrections (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Additions to "Light Music" [these stanzas not in earlier edition SP 62-78], TS (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - Untitled, table of contents for planned collection, [ca. 1993] (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - The Hudson Letter (Gallery Press 1995)
      - Part One
      - "Albums," MS and TS [variant title: The Travel Section, The Wild West Picture Book] (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - "Anglo-Irish Clerihews," TS (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - "The Bird Life of Kinsale," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - "Burbles," MS and TS [variant title: "Squeals"] (Box 17, Folder 20)
      - "Inscription from the Old Bath House," MS (Box 17, Folder 21)
      - "Noon at St. Michael's," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 22)
      - "An Orphan at the Door," MS and TS [variant title: "Fragile As a Shell"] (Box 17, Folder 23)
      - "Pygmalion and Galatea," TS (Box 17, Folder 24)
      - "River Rhymes," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 25)
      - "The Yaddo Letter," TS (Box 17, Folder 26)
      - "The Yaddo Letter," TS (Box 17, Folder 27)
      - "The Yaddo Letter," source material (Box 17, Folder 28)
      - "The Yaddo Letter," proofs [from American Poetry Review] with corrections (Box OP2)
      - "The Yaddo Letter," Gallery Press proofs with corrections (Box 17, Folder 29)
      - "The Yaddo Letter," Gallery Press loose sheets with corrections (Box 17, Folder 30)
      - "The Yaddo Letter," Gallery Books edition, 3 copies (Box 17, Folder 31)
      - Part Two, "The Hudson Letter"
      - Winter; a short walk from the 10th St. Pier, TS (Box 17, Folder 32)
      - I. "Last Night," TS (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - II. "Global Village," TS (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - III. "Waterfront," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - IV. "'To Mrs. Moore at Inishannon,'" TS (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - V. "Insider Trading Reports are Linked to Price of Bonds," TS (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - VI. "Sneakers'," TS (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - VII. "When his wronged wife Procne sat him down to eat," TS (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - VIII. "'Nature, not having included me in her plan," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - IX. "Auden on St. Mark's Place," TS (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - X. "Chinatown," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - XI. "Alien Nation," TS (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - XII. "Sappho in 'Judith's Room,'" MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - XIII. "Beauty and the Beast," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - "Domnei," TS (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - "Key West," TS (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - "Key West," source materials (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - "Imbolc: JBY," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - "The Small Rain," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - Tradition and the Individual Talent [originally planned for HL], TS (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - The Hudson Letter, early draft, TS and notes (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - The Hudson Letter, early draft, MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - The Hudson Letter, complete typescript (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - The Hudson Letter, complete typescript (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - The Hudson Letter, Gallery Press proofs (Box 18, Folder 24)
      - The Hudson Letter, jacket copy and editorial correspondence (Box 18, Folder 25)
      - The Hudson Letter, corrected Gallery Press proofs (Box 18, Folder 26)
      - The Hudson Letter, Wake Forest University Press proofs (Box 18, Folder 27)
      - The Hudson Letter, drafts and notes (Box 18, Folder 28)
      - The Hudson Letter, sources (Box 18, Folder 29)
      - Introduction for DM at U.S. launch of Hudson Letters, Ireland House, 23 January 1996 (Box 18, Folder 30)
      - Hudson Letter revisions, September 1999 [See Subseries 2.1: The Yellow Book, "The Yellow Book and The Hudson Letter revisions"] (Box -, -)
      - The Yellow Book (1997)
      - Landscape, TS (Box 18, Folder 31)
      - I. Night Thoughts, MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 32)
      - II. Axel's Castle, MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 33)
      - III. At the Shelbourne, MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 34)
      - IV. 'shiver in your tenement,' MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 35)
      - V. Schopenhauer's Day, MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 36)
      - VI. To Eugene Lambe in Heaven, TS (Box 18, Folder 37)
      - VII. An Bonnán Buí, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - VIII. Remembering the '90s, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - IX. At the Gate Theatre, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - X. The Idiocy of Human Aspiration, TS (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - XI. At the Chelsea Arts Club, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - XII. Aphrodite's Pool, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - XIII. Dusk, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - XIV. Rue des Beaux-Arts, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - XV. Smoke, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - XVI. America Deserta, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - XVII. The World of J. G. Farrell, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - XVIII. Death in Bangor, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - XIX. On the Automation of the Irish Lights, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - XX. Christmas in Kinsale, MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 14)
      - "Bad Girls" [originally planned for YB], MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 15)
      - "The Gold Rush" [originally planned for YB], MS and TS (Box 19, Folder 16)
      - The Yellow Book, Drafts of title and contents (Box 19, Folder 17)
      - The Yellow Book, TS with corrections (Box 19, Folder 18)
      - The Yellow Book, TS with corrections (Box 19, Folder 19)
      - The Yellow Book, Notes and materials (Box 19, Folder 20)
      - The Yellow Book, Source materials (Box 19, Folder 21)
      - The Yellow Book, Source materials (Box 19, Folder 22)
      - The Yellow Book, Gallery Press material (Box 19, Folder 23)
      - The Yellow Book, Gallery Press proofs (Box 19, Folder 24)
      - The Yellow Book and The Hudson Letter revisions, September 1999 (Box 19, Folder 25)
      - Scrapbook with Yellow Book materials [See Subseries 2.2: Scrapbook, 1996-1997] (Box -, -)
      - Words In the Air (1998)
      - Proofs and associated Gallery Press material (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Collected Poems (1999) and Selected Poems (2000)
        This section includes both new poems and the manuscripts of older poems which have clearly been revised for this publication.
      - "After Michelangelo," MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - "The Apotheosis of Tins," TS (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - "Camus in Ulster," TS (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - "Dawn at St. Patricks," TS (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - "A Dirge," TS (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - "The Dream Play," MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - "from "Gramsci's Ashes," TS (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - "Ghosts," MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - "How to Live," TS (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - "I am Raftery," TS (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - "The Idiocy of Human Aspiration," TS [revised version] (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - "The Mayo Tao," TS (Box 20, Folder 13)
      - "Night and Day," TS (Box 20, Folder 14)
      - "Northern Star," MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 15)
      - "Ovid in Love," TS (Box 20, Folder 16)
      - "The Race," TS (Box 20, Folder 17)
      - "Rock Music," TS [See also Uncollected poems, "Toward the Light"] (Box 20, Folder 18)
      - "Roman Script," notes and drafts, MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 19)
      - "Roman Script," final proofs (Box 20, Folder 20)
      - "Roman Script," artwork (Box 20, Folder 21)
      - "St. Patrick's Day, MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 22)
      - "Shapes and Shadows," MS, TS, and proof [includes TLS from Adrian Rice, 11 October 2000] (Box 20, Folder 23)
      - "A Siren," TS (Box 20, Folder 24)
      - "'Songs of Praise,'" MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 25)
      - "Squince," TS (Box 20, Folder 26)
      - "Stanzas for Mary Stuart," MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 27)
      - "A Swim in Co. Wicklow," MS and TS (Box 20, Folder 28)
      - Selected Poems (2000), proofs (Box 20, Folder 29)
      - Selected Poems, covers (Box 20, Folder 30)
      - Notes for Contents of Collected Poems and Selected Poems (Box 20, Folder 31)
      - Resistance Days (2001)
      - "Resistance Days," TS (Box 20, Folder 32)
      - The Seaside Cemetery: A Version of "Le Cimetière Marin" by Paul Valéry (2001)
      - "The Seaside Cemetery," TS [1] (Box 20, Folder 33)
      - "The Seaside Cemetery," TS [2] (Box 20, Folder 34)
      - "The Seaside Cemetery," TS [3] (Box 20, Folder 35)